Guide to the Douglas Clyde Macintosh Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Douglas Clyde Macintosh Papers
1906-1978
RG 50
Yale University Divinity School Library
5.25
(9 boxes)
Letters, writings, and memorabilia document Macintosh's life and work. Douglas Clyde Macintosh was Professor of Theology at Yale from 1909 to 1942.
Macintosh, Douglas Clyde, 1877-1948
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Macintosh family.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1877 Born in Canada
1903 B.A., McMaster University, Toronto
1907 Ordained into Baptist ministry Professor of Bible and Systematic Theology at Brandon College, Manitoba
1909 Ph.D., University of Chicago
1909-1916 Assistant Professor of Systematic Theology, YDS
WWI Chaplain to Canadian forces in France; YMCA worker with American troops
1916-1933 Dwight Professor of Theology, YDS
1920-1938 Chairman of the Religion Department, Yale
1924-1925 Nathaniel W. Taylor Lecturer
1926 D.D., Colgate University
1931 Denied U.S. citizenship by Supreme Court, for refusal in advance to bear arms in defense of U.S.
1932 LL.D., McMaster University
1933-1942 Dwight Professor of Theology and Philosophy of Religion
1942 Suffered paralytic stroke
1942-1948 Professor Emeritus
1948 Died in Hamden, Connecticut
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1907-1946, n.d.
II. Writings, 1911-1945
III. Notes, 1906-1910,n.d.
IV. Biographical Documentation,
This collection provides a good overview of Macintosh's professional life, which was spent primarily at Yale Divinity School. The correspondence in Series I is not extensive, but includes letters from colleagues such as John Baillie, Josiah Royce, and Henry Nelson Wieman. Macintosh's thoughts on theological subjects are expressed in a few letters, but most are more routine exchanges related to his writings, students, and engagements.
The Writings of Series II include offprints and published pamphlets as well as typescript manuscripts. One of these manuscripts "The Plain Man's Soliloquy" has not been published.
The Notes of Series III include extensive handwritten notes taken by Macintosh and notes taken by a student in Macintosh's Systematic Theology course in 1940.
Most significant among the biographical materials of Series IV is a large scrapbook that includes correspondence, clippings, and documents related to Macintosh's citizenship case. A native of Canada, Macintosh was denied United States citizenship by the Supreme Court because of his stance against bearing arms.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1907-1946, n.d.
II. Writings, 1911-1945
III. Notes, 1906-1910,n.d.
IV. Biographical Documentation
Theology -- Methodology -- History; Educators; Macintosh, Douglas Clyde, 1877-1948; Yale University. Divinity School -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1907-1910; Series I
  - Incl. from Josiah Royce, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incl. from George A. Coe, Josiah Royce, George B. Foster, 1912-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Incl. from John Baillie, William Ernest Hocking, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incl. from Albert Schweitzer, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incl. from J. Gresham Machen, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incl. from James B. Pratt, to Wilbur Smith, 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Incl. from John Dewey (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings, Series II
  - In published format
    - "Empirical Theology and Some of Its Misunderstanders" The Review of Religion, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - God in a World at War, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Hope of Immortality" Religion in Life, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Is Belief in the Historicity of Jesus Indispensable to Christian Faith?" The American Journal of Theology, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Is Theology Reducible to Mythology?" The Review of Religion, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Meaning of God in Modern Religion" The Journal of Religion, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Method of Religious Inquiry" Religion in Life, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The New Christianity and World-Conversion" The American Journal of Theology, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Pragmatic Element in the Teaching of Paul" The American Journal of Theology, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Reaction Against Metaphysics in Theology" (DCM dissertation), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Theology and Metaphysics" Twentieth Century Philosophy, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Theology, Valuational or Existential?" The Review of Religion, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Troeltsch's Theory of Religious Knowledge" The American Journal of Theology, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "What is the Christian Religion?" The Harvard Theological Review, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Book review, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "A Conversation About God" Christian Century (scrapbook of clippings) (Box OV2)
  - Typescript manuscripts
    - "The Plain Man's Soliloquy", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11-16)
    - "Charles Allen Dinsmore as Minister and Theologian" (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Ordination prayer, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "The Reasonableness of Christianity", 1926 (Box 6)
    - "The Problem of Religious Knowledge", 1915 (Box 6)
- Notes, Series III
  - Notes by DCM
    - Small notebooks, 1906-1910, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Small notebooks, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
    - Large notebook - bibliography of works on theology, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Looseleaf notes, incl. taken from books in DCM's library (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Notes on DCM's Systematic Theology course
    - Taken by H. E. Finger, Jr., 1940 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Biographical Documentation, n.d.; Series IV
  - "Out of the Wilderness: A Philosophical Biography of Douglas Clyde Macintosh" by W. Preston Warren, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Biographical material: obituary, photographs, article re. DCM, 1927-1948 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Centennial Tribute compiled by Paul Douglas Macintosh Keane: tributes from former colleagues of DCM, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Bibliography of DCM's works compiled by Raymond Morris (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous collected material, 1911-1942 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Biographical tribute to Emily Powell Macintosh, first wife of DCM, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Pamphlet re. Douglas Clyde Macintosh Fellowship in Theology and the Philosophy of Religion established by Hope Conklin Macintosh, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Annotated Bible (Box 6)
  - Presentation copy of The Nature of Religious Experience: Essays in Honor of Douglas Clyde Macintosh", signed by the authors of the essays, 1937 (Box 7)
    Scope and Contents
    This volume was received from Alexander Mack Memorial Library, Special Collections, Bridgewater College, Bridgewater, Virginia in 2013, a gift in honor of Dr. William W. Thomas and Douglas Clyde Macintosh. The book was received by Bridgewater as an estate gift from Dr. Thomas, professor of Religion and Philosophy, James Madison University, 1971-2003.
  - Scrapbook related to DCM's citizenship case (Box OV1)